<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text>

<story>
<title>Hansel AND Gretel</title>

<p>Hard by a great forest dwelt a poor <character name="Father" role="woodcutter">wood-cutter</character> with his <character name="Stepmother" role="villain">wife</character> and his
two children. The boy was called <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character> and the girl <character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character>. He had
little to bite and to break, and once when great <define>dearth</define> fell on the
land, he could no longer procure even daily bread. Now when he thought
over this by night in his bed, and tossed about in his anxiety, he
groaned and said to his <character name="Stepmother" role="villain">wife</character>: <dialog>‘What is to become of us? How are we
to feed our poor children, when we no longer have anything even for
ourselves?’ ‘I’ll tell you what, husband,’</dialog> answered the <character name="Stepmother" role="villain">woman</character>, <dialog>‘early
tomorrow morning we will take the children out into the forest to where
it is the thickest; there we will light a fire for them, and give each
of them one more piece of bread, and then we will go to our work and
leave them alone. They will not find the way home again, and we shall be
rid of them.’ ‘No, wife,’</dialog> said the <character name="Father" role="woodcutter">man</character>, <dialog>‘I will not do that; how can I
bear to leave my children alone in the forest?--the wild animals would
soon come and tear them to pieces.’ ‘O, you fool!’</dialog> said she, <dialog>‘then we
must all four die of hunger, you may as well plane the planks for our
coffins,’</dialog> and she left him no peace until he consented. <dialog>‘But I feel very
sorry for the poor children, all the same,’</dialog> said the <character name="Father" role="woodcutter">man</character>.</p>

<p>The two children had also not been able to sleep for hunger, and had
heard what their <character name="Stepmother" role="villain">stepmother</character> had said to their <character name="Father" role="woodcutter">father</character>. <character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character> wept
bitter tears, and said to <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character>: <dialog>‘Now all is over with us.’ ‘Be quiet,
<character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character>,’</dialog> said <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character>, <dialog>‘do not distress yourself, I will soon find a way
to help us.’</dialog> And when the old folks had fallen asleep, he got up, put
on his little coat, opened the door below, and crept outside. The moon
shone brightly, and the white pebbles which lay in front of the house
glittered like real silver pennies. <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character> stooped and stuffed the
little pocket of his coat with as many as he could get in. Then he went
back and said to <character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character>: <dialog>‘Be comforted, dear little sister, and sleep in
peace, God will not forsake us,’</dialog> and he lay down again in his bed. When
day dawned, but before the sun had risen, the <character name="Stepmother" role="villain">woman</character> came and awoke the
two children, saying: <dialog>‘Get up, you <define>sluggards</define>! we are going into the
forest to fetch wood.’</dialog> She gave each a little piece of bread, and said:
<dialog>‘There is something for your dinner, but do not eat it up before then,
for you will get nothing else.’</dialog> <character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character> took the bread under her apron,
as <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character> had the pebbles in his pocket. Then they all set out together
on the way to the forest. When they had walked a short time, <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character>
stood still and peeped back at the house, and did so again and again.
His <character name="Father" role="woodcutter">father</character> said: <dialog>‘<character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character>, what are you looking at there and staying
behind for? Pay attention, and do not forget how to use your legs.’ ‘Ah,
father,’</dialog> said <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character>, <dialog>‘I am looking at my little white cat, which is
sitting up on the roof, and wants to say goodbye to me.’</dialog> The wife said:
<dialog>‘Fool, that is not your little cat, that is the morning sun which is
shining on the chimneys.’</dialog> <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character>, however, had not been looking back at
the cat, but had been constantly throwing one of the white pebble-stones
out of his pocket on the road.</p>

<p>When they had reached the middle of the forest, the <character name="Father" role="woodcutter">father</character> said: <dialog>‘Now,
children, pile up some wood, and I will light a fire that you may not
be cold.’</dialog> <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character> and <character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character> gathered brushwood together, as high as a
little hill. The brushwood was lighted, and when the flames were burning
very high, the <character name="Stepmother" role="villain">woman</character> said: <dialog>‘Now, children, lay yourselves down by the
fire and rest, we will go into the forest and cut some wood. When we
have done, we will come back and fetch you away.’</dialog></p>

<p><character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character> and <character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character> sat by the fire, and when noon came, each ate a little
piece of bread, and as they heard the strokes of the wood-axe they
believed that their <character name="Father" role="woodcutter">father</character> was near. It was not the axe, however, but
a branch which he had fastened to a withered tree which the wind was
blowing backwards and forwards. And as they had been sitting such a long
time, their eyes closed with fatigue, and they fell fast asleep. When
at last they awoke, it was already dark night. <character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character> began to cry and
said: <dialog>‘How are we to get out of the forest now?’</dialog> But <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character> comforted
her and said: <dialog>‘Just wait a little, until the moon has risen, and then we
will soon find the way.’</dialog> And when the full moon had risen, <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character> took
his little sister by the hand, and followed the pebbles which shone like
newly-coined silver pieces, and showed them the way.</p>

<p>They walked the whole night long, and by break of day came once more
to their <character name="Father" role="woodcutter">father</character>’s house. They knocked at the door, and when the <character name="Stepmother" role="villain">woman</character>
opened it and saw that it was <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character> and <character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character>, she said: <dialog>‘You naughty
children, why have you slept so long in the forest?--we thought you were
never coming back at all!’</dialog> The <character name="Father" role="woodcutter">father</character>, however, rejoiced, for it had cut
him to the heart to leave them behind alone.</p>

<p>Not long afterwards, there was once more great <define>dearth</define> throughout the
land, and the children heard their <character name="Stepmother" role="villain">mother</character> saying at night to their
<character name="Father" role="woodcutter">father</character>: <dialog>‘Everything is eaten again, we have one half loaf left, and that
is the end. The children must go, we will take them farther into the
wood, so that they will not find their way out again; there is no other
means of saving ourselves!’</dialog> The <character name="Father" role="woodcutter">man</character>’s heart was heavy, and he thought:
‘It would be better for you to share the last mouthful with your
children.’ The <character name="Stepmother" role="villain">woman</character>, however, would listen to nothing that he had to
say, but scolded and reproached him. He who says A must say B, likewise,
and as he had yielded the first time, he had to do so a second time
also.</p>

<p>The children, however, were still awake and had heard the conversation.
When the old folks were asleep, <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character> again got up, and wanted to go
out and pick up pebbles as he had done before, but the <character name="Stepmother" role="villain">woman</character> had locked
the door, and <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character> could not get out. Nevertheless he comforted his
little sister, and said: <dialog>‘Do not cry, <character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character>, go to sleep quietly, the
good God will help us.’</dialog></p>

<p>Early in the morning came the <character name="Stepmother" role="villain">woman</character>, and took the children out of their
beds. Their piece of bread was given to them, but it was still smaller
than the time before. On the way into the forest <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character> crumbled his
in his pocket, and often stood still and threw a morsel on the ground.
<dialog>‘<character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character>, why do you stop and look round?’</dialog> said the <character name="Father" role="woodcutter">father</character>, <dialog>‘go on.’ ‘I
am looking back at my little pigeon which is sitting on the roof, and
wants to say goodbye to me,’</dialog> answered <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character>. <dialog>‘Fool!’</dialog> said the <character name="Stepmother" role="villain">woman</character>,
<dialog>‘that is not your little pigeon, that is the morning sun that is shining
on the chimney.’</dialog> <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character>, however little by little, threw all the crumbs
on the path.</p>

<p>The <character name="Stepmother" role="villain">woman</character> led the children still deeper into the forest, where they had
never in their lives been before. Then a great fire was again made, and
the <character name="Stepmother" role="villain">mother</character> said: <dialog>‘Just sit there, you children, and when you are tired
you may sleep a little; we are going into the forest to cut wood, and in
the evening when we are done, we will come and fetch you away.’</dialog> When
it was noon, <character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character> shared her piece of bread with <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character>, who had
scattered his by the way. Then they fell asleep and evening passed, but
no one came to the poor children. They did not awake until it was dark
night, and <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character> comforted his little sister and said: <dialog>‘Just wait,
<character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character>, until the moon rises, and then we shall see the crumbs of bread
which I have strewn about, they will show us our way home again.’</dialog> When
the moon came they set out, but they found no crumbs, for the many
thousands of birds which fly about in the woods and fields had picked
them all up. <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character> said to <character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character>: <dialog>‘We shall soon find the way,’</dialog> but
they did not find it. They walked the whole night and all the next day
too from morning till evening, but they did not get out of the forest,
and were very hungry, for they had nothing to eat but two or three
berries, which grew on the ground. And as they were so weary that their
legs would carry them no longer, they lay down beneath a tree and fell
asleep.</p>

<p>It was now three mornings since they had left their <character name="Father" role="woodcutter">father</character>’s house. They
began to walk again, but they always came deeper into the forest, and if
help did not come soon, they must die of hunger and weariness. When it
was mid-day, they saw a beautiful snow-white bird sitting on a <define>bough</define>,
which sang so delightfully that they stood still and listened to it. And
when its song was over, it spread its wings and flew away before them,
and they followed it until they reached a little house, on the roof of
which it alighted; and when they approached the little house they saw
that it was built of bread and covered with cakes, but that the windows
were of clear sugar. <dialog>‘We will set to work on that,’</dialog> said <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character>, <dialog>‘and
have a good meal. I will eat a bit of the roof, and you <character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character>, can eat
some of the window, it will taste sweet.’</dialog> <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character> reached up above, and
broke off a little of the roof to try how it tasted, and <character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character> leant
against the window and nibbled at the panes. Then a soft voice cried
from the parlour:

 <dialog>‘Nibble, nibble, gnaw,
  Who is nibbling at my little house?’</dialog>

<p>The children answered:</p>

 <dialog>‘The wind, the wind,
  The heaven-born wind,’</dialog></p>

<p>and went on eating without disturbing themselves. <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character>, who liked the
taste of the roof, tore down a great piece of it, and <character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character> pushed out
the whole of one round window-pane, sat down, and enjoyed herself with
it. Suddenly the door opened, and a <character name="Witch" role="antagonist">woman</character> as old as the hills, who
supported herself on crutches, came creeping out. <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character> and <character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character> were
so terribly frightened that they let fall what they had in their
hands. The old <character name="Witch" role="antagonist">woman</character>, however, nodded her head, and said: <dialog>‘Oh, you dear
children, who has brought you here? do come in, and stay with me. No
harm shall happen to you.’</dialog> She took them both by the hand, and led them
into her little house. Then good food was set before them, milk and
pancakes, with sugar, apples, and nuts. Afterwards two pretty little
beds were covered with clean white linen, and <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character> and <character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character> lay down
in them, and thought they were in heaven.</p>

<p>The old <character name="Witch" role="antagonist">woman</character> had only pretended to be so kind; she was in reality
a wicked <character name="Stepmother" role="villain">witch</character>, who lay in wait for children, and had only built the
little house of bread in order to entice them there. When a child fell
into her power, she killed it, cooked and ate it, and that was a feast
day with her. Witches have red eyes, and cannot see far, but they have
a keen scent like the beasts, and are aware when human beings draw near.
When <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character> and <character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character> came into her neighbourhood, she laughed with
malice, and said mockingly: <dialog>‘I have them, they shall not escape me
again!’</dialog> Early in the morning before the children were awake, she was
already up, and when she saw both of them sleeping and looking so
pretty, with their plump and rosy cheeks she muttered to herself: <dialog>‘That
will be a dainty mouthful!’</dialog> Then she seized <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character> with her shrivelled
hand, carried him into a little stable, and locked him in behind a
grated door. Scream as he might, it would not help him. Then she went to
<character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character>, shook her till she awoke, and cried: <dialog>‘Get up, lazy thing, fetch
some water, and cook something good for your brother, he is in the
stable outside, and is to be made fat. When he is fat, I will eat him.’</dialog>
<character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character> began to weep bitterly, but it was all in vain, for she was
forced to do what the wicked <character name="Stepmother" role="villain">witch</character> commanded.</p>

<p>And now the best food was cooked for poor <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character>, but <character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character> got nothing
but crab-shells. Every morning the <character name="Witch" role="antagonist">woman</character> crept to the little stable, and
cried: <dialog>‘<character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character>, stretch out your finger that I may feel if you will soon
be fat.’</dialog> <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character>, however, stretched out a little bone to her, and
the old <character name="Witch" role="antagonist">woman</character>, who had dim eyes, could not see it, and thought it was
<character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character>’s finger, and was astonished that there was no way of fattening
him. When four weeks had gone by, and <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character> still remained thin, she
was seized with impatience and would not wait any longer. <dialog>‘Now, then,
<character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character>,’</dialog> she cried to the girl, <dialog>‘stir yourself, and bring some water.
Let <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character> be fat or lean, tomorrow I will kill him, and cook him.’</dialog> Ah,
how the poor little sister did lament when she had to fetch the water,
and how her tears did flow down her cheeks! <dialog>‘Dear God, do help us,’</dialog> she
cried. <dialog>‘If the wild beasts in the forest had but devoured us, we should
at any rate have died together.’ ‘Just keep your noise to yourself,’</dialog>
said the old <character name="Witch" role="antagonist">woman</character>, <dialog>‘it won’t help you at all.’</dialog></p>

<p>Early in the morning, <character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character> had to go out and hang up the cauldron with
the water, and light the fire. <dialog>‘We will bake first,’</dialog> said the old <character name="Witch" role="antagonist">woman</character>,
<dialog>‘I have already heated the oven, and kneaded the dough.’</dialog> She pushed poor
<character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character> out to the oven, from which flames of fire were already darting.
<dialog>‘Creep in,’</dialog> said the witch, <dialog>‘and see if it is properly heated, so that
we can put the bread in.’</dialog> And once <character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character> was inside, she intended to
shut the oven and let her bake in it, and then she would eat her, too.
But <character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character> saw what she had in mind, and said: <dialog>‘I do not know how I am
to do it; how do I get in?’ ‘Silly goose,’</dialog> said the old <character name="Witch" role="antagonist">woman</character>. <dialog>The door
is big enough; just look, I can get in myself!’</dialog> and she crept up and
thrust her head into the oven. Then <character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character> gave her a push that drove
her far into it, and shut the iron door, and fastened the bolt. Oh! then
she began to howl quite horribly, but <character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character> ran away and the godless
<character name="Stepmother" role="villain">witch</character> was miserably burnt to death.</p>

<p><character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character>, however, ran like lightning to <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character>, opened his little stable,
and cried: <dialog>‘<character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character>, we are saved! The old <character name="Stepmother" role="villain">witch</character> is dead!’</dialog> Then <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character>
sprang like a bird from its cage when the door is opened. How they did
rejoice and embrace each other, and dance about and kiss each other! And
as they had no longer any need to fear her, they went into the <character name="Stepmother" role="villain">witch</character>’s
house, and in every corner there stood chests full of pearls and jewels.
<dialog>‘These are far better than pebbles!’</dialog> said <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character>, and thrust into his
pockets whatever could be got in, and <character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character> said: <dialog>‘I, too, will take
something home with me,’</dialog> and filled her <define>pinafore</define> full. <dialog>‘But now we must
be off,’</dialog> said <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character>, <dialog>‘that we may get out of the <character name="Stepmother" role="villain">witch</character>’s forest.’</dialog></p>

<p>When they had walked for two hours, they came to a great stretch of
water. <dialog>‘We cannot cross,’</dialog> said <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character>, <dialog>‘I see no foot-plank, and no
bridge.’ ‘And there is also no ferry,’</dialog> answered <character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character>, <dialog>‘but a white
duck is swimming there: if I ask her, she will help us over.’</dialog> Then she
cried:

 <dialog>‘Little duck, little duck, <slang>dost thou</slang> see,
  <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character> and <character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character> are waiting for thee?
  There’s never a plank, or bridge in sight,
  Take us across on thy back so white.’</dialog></p>

<p>The duck came to them, and <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character> seated himself on its back, and told
his sister to sit by him. <dialog>‘No,’</dialog> replied <character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character>, <dialog>‘that will be too heavy
for the little duck; she shall take us across, one after the other.’</dialog> The
good little duck did so, and when they were once safely across and had
walked for a short time, the forest seemed to be more and more familiar
to them, and at length they saw from afar their <character name="Father" role="woodcutter">father</character>’s house. Then
they began to run, rushed into the parlour, and threw themselves round
their <character name="Father" role="woodcutter">father</character>’s neck. The <character name="Father" role="woodcutter">man</character> had not known one happy hour since he had
left the children in the forest; the <character name="Stepmother" role="villain">woman</character>, however, was dead. <character name="Gretel" role="younger sibling">Gretel</character>
emptied her <define>pinafore</define> until pearls and precious stones ran about the
room, and <character name="Hansel" role="older sibling">Hansel</character> threw one handful after another out of his pocket to
add to them. Then all anxiety was at an end, and they lived together
in perfect happiness. My tale is done, there runs a mouse; whosoever
catches it, may make himself a big fur cap out of it.</p>
</story>
<theme>Survival and Resilience</theme>


<story>
<title>LITTLE RED-CAP [LITTLE RED RIDING HOOD]</title>

<p>Once upon a time there was a dear little girl who was loved by everyone
who looked at her, but most of all by her <character name="Grandmother" role="supporting">grandmother</character>, and there was
nothing that she would not have given to the child. Once she gave her a
little cap of red velvet, which suited her so well that she would never
wear anything else; so she was always called ‘<character name="Little Red-Cap" role="protagonist">Little Red-Cap</character>.’</p>

<p>One day her mother said to her: <dialog>‘Come, Little Red-Cap, here is a piece
of cake and a bottle of wine; take them to your grandmother, she is ill
and weak, and they will do her good. Set out before it gets hot, and
when you are going, walk nicely and quietly and do not run off the path,
or you may fall and break the bottle, and then your grandmother will
get nothing; and when you go into her room, don’t forget to say, “Good
morning”, and don’t peep into every corner before you do it.’</dialog></p>

<p><dialog>‘I will take great care,’</dialog> said <character name="Little Red-Cap" role="protagonist">Little Red-Cap</character> to her mother, and gave
her hand on it.</p>

<p>The <character name="Grandmother" role="supporting">grandmother</character> lived out in the wood, half a <define>league</define> from the village,
and just as <character name="Little Red-Cap" role="protagonist">Little Red-Cap</character> entered the wood, a <character name="Wolf" role="antagonist">wolf</character> met her. Red-Cap
did not know what a wicked creature he was, and was not at all afraid of
him.</p>

<p><dialog>‘Good day, Little Red-Cap,’</dialog> said he.</p>

<p><dialog>‘Thank you kindly, wolf.’</dialog></p>

<p><dialog>‘Whither away so early, Little Red-Cap?’</dialog></p>

<p><dialog>‘To my grandmother’s.’</dialog></p>

<p><dialog>‘What have you got in your apron?’</dialog></p>

<p><dialog>‘Cake and wine; yesterday was baking-day, so poor sick grandmother is to
have something good, to make her stronger.’</dialog></p>

<p><dialog>‘Where does your grandmother live, Little Red-Cap?’</dialog></p>

<p><dialog>‘A good quarter of a <define>league</define> farther on in the wood; her house stands
under the three large oak-trees, the nut-trees are just below; you
surely must know it,’</dialog> replied <character name="Little Red-Cap" role="protagonist">Little Red-Cap</character>.</p>

<p>The <character name="Wolf" role="antagonist">wolf</character> thought to himself: ‘What a tender young creature! what a nice
plump mouthful--she will be better to eat than the old woman. I must
act craftily, so as to catch both.’ So he walked for a short time by
the side of <character name="Little Red-Cap" role="protagonist">Little Red-Cap</character>, and then he said: <dialog>‘See, Little Red-Cap, how
pretty the flowers are about here--why do you not look round? I believe,
too, that you do not hear how sweetly the little birds are singing; you
walk gravely along as if you were going to school, while everything else
out here in the wood is merry.’</dialog></p>

<p><character name="Little Red-Cap" role="protagonist">Little Red-Cap</character> raised her eyes, and when she saw the sunbeams dancing
here and there through the trees, and pretty flowers growing everywhere,
she thought: ‘Suppose I take grandmother a fresh <define>nosegay</define>; that would
please her too. It is so early in the day that I shall still get there
in good time’; and so she ran from the path into the wood to look for
flowers. And whenever she had picked one, she fancied that she saw a
still prettier one farther on, and ran after it, and so got deeper and
deeper into the wood.</p>

<p>Meanwhile the <character name="Wolf" role="antagonist">wolf</character> ran straight to the <character name="Grandmother" role="supporting">grandmother</character>’s house and knocked
at the door.</p>

<p><dialog>‘Who is there?’</dialog></p>

<p><dialog>‘Little Red-Cap,’</dialog> replied the <character name="Wolf" role="antagonist">wolf</character>. <dialog>‘She is bringing cake and wine; open
the door.’</dialog></p>

<p><dialog>‘Lift the latch,’</dialog> called out the <character name="Grandmother" role="supporting">grandmother</character>, <dialog>‘I am too weak, and cannot
get up.’</dialog></p>

<p>The <character name="Wolf" role="antagonist">wolf</character> lifted the latch, the door sprang open, and without saying a
word he went straight to the <character name="Grandmother" role="supporting">grandmother</character>’s bed, and devoured her. Then
he put on her clothes, dressed himself in her cap laid himself in bed
and drew the curtains.</p>

<p><character name="Little Red-Cap" role="protagonist">Little Red-Cap</character>, however, had been running about picking flowers,
and when she had gathered so many that she could carry no more, she
remembered her <character name="Grandmother" role="supporting">grandmother</character>, and set out on the way to her.</p>

<p>She was surprised to find the cottage-door standing open, and when she
went into the room, she had such a strange feeling that she said to
herself: <dialog>‘Oh dear! how uneasy I feel today, and at other times I like
being with grandmother so much.’</dialog> She called out: <dialog>‘Good morning,’</dialog> but
received no answer; so she went to the bed and drew back the curtains.
There lay her <character name="Grandmother" role="supporting">grandmother</character> with her cap pulled far over her face, and
looking very strange.</p>

<p><dialog>‘Oh! grandmother,’</dialog> she said, <dialog>‘what big ears you have!’</dialog></p>

<p><dialog>‘The better to hear you with, my child,’</dialog> was the reply.</p>

<p><dialog>‘But, grandmother, what big eyes you have!’</dialog> she said.</p>

<p><dialog>‘The better to see you with, my dear.’</dialog></p>

<p><dialog>‘But, grandmother, what large hands you have!’</dialog></p>

<p><dialog>‘The better to hug you with.’</dialog></p>

<p><dialog>‘Oh! but, grandmother, what a terrible big mouth you have!’</dialog></p>

<p><dialog>‘The better to eat you with!’</dialog></p>

<p>And scarcely had the <character name="Wolf" role="antagonist">wolf</character> said this, than with one bound he was out of
bed and swallowed up Red-Cap.</p>

<p>When the <character name="Wolf" role="antagonist">wolf</character> had appeased his appetite, he lay down again in the bed,
fell asleep and began to snore very loud. The <character name="Huntsman" role="supporting">huntsman</character> was just passing
the house, and thought to himself: ‘How the old woman is snoring! I must
just see if she wants anything.’ So he went into the room, and when he
came to the bed, he saw that the <character name="Wolf" role="antagonist">wolf</character> was lying in it. <dialog>‘Do I find you
here, you old sinner!’</dialog> said he. <dialog>‘I have long sought you!’</dialog> Then just as
he was going to fire at him, it occurred to him that the <character name="Wolf" role="antagonist">wolf</character> might have
devoured the <character name="Grandmother" role="supporting">grandmother</character>, and that she might still be saved, so he did
not fire, but took a pair of scissors, and began to cut open the stomach
of the sleeping <character name="Wolf" role="antagonist">wolf</character>. When he had made two snips, he saw the little
Red-Cap shining, and then he made two snips more, and the little girl
sprang out, crying: <dialog>‘Ah, how frightened I have been! How dark it was
inside the wolf’</dialog>; and after that the aged <character name="Grandmother" role="supporting">grandmother</character> came out alive
also, but scarcely able to breathe. Red-Cap, however, quickly fetched
great stones with which they filled the <character name="Wolf" role="antagonist">wolf</character>’s belly, and when he awoke,
he wanted to run away, but the stones were so heavy that he collapsed at
once, and fell dead.</p>

<p>Then all three were delighted. The <character name="Huntsman" role="supporting">huntsman</character> drew off the <character name="Wolf" role="antagonist">wolf</character>’s skin and
went home with it; the <character name="Grandmother" role="supporting">grandmother</character> ate the cake and drank the wine which
Red-Cap had brought, and revived, but Red-Cap thought to herself: ‘As
long as I live, I will never by myself leave the path, to run into the
wood, when my mother has forbidden me to do so.’</p>

<p>It also related that once when Red-Cap was again taking cakes to the old
<character name="Grandmother" role="supporting">grandmother</character>, another <character name="Wolf" role="antagonist">wolf</character> spoke to her, and tried to entice her from the
path. Red-Cap, however, was on her guard, and went straight forward on
her way, and told her <character name="Grandmother" role="supporting">grandmother</character> that she had met the <character name="Wolf" role="antagonist">wolf</character>, and that he
had said <dialog>‘good morning’</dialog> to her, but with such a wicked look in his eyes,
that if they had not been on the public road she was certain he would
have eaten her up. <dialog>‘Well,’</dialog> said the <character name="Grandmother" role="supporting">grandmother</character>, <dialog>‘we will shut the door,
that he may not come in.’</dialog> Soon afterwards the <character name="Wolf" role="antagonist">wolf</character> knocked, and cried:
<dialog>‘Open the door, grandmother, I am Little Red-Cap, and am bringing you
some cakes.’</dialog> But they did not speak, or open the door, so the grey-beard
stole twice or thrice round the house, and at last jumped on the roof,
intending to wait until Red-Cap went home in the evening, and then to
steal after her and devour her in the darkness. But the <character name="Grandmother" role="supporting">grandmother</character>
saw what was in his thoughts. In front of the house was a great stone
trough, so she said to the child: <dialog>‘Take the pail, Red-Cap; I made some
sausages yesterday, so carry the water in which I boiled them to the
trough.’</dialog> Red-Cap carried until the great trough was quite full. Then the
smell of the sausages reached the <character name="Wolf" role="antagonist">wolf</character>, and he sniffed and peeped down,
and at last stretched out his neck so far that he could no longer keep
his footing and began to slip, and slipped down from the roof straight
into the great trough, and was drowned. But Red-Cap went joyously home,
and no one ever did anything to harm her again.</p>
</story>
<theme>Innocence vs. Danger</theme>


<story>
<title>RAPUNZEL</title>

<p>There were once a <character name="The Man" role="husband">man</character> and a <character name="The Woman" role="wife">woman</character> who had long in vain wished for a
child. At length the <character name="The Woman" role="wife">woman</character> hoped that God was about to grant her desire.
These people had a little window at the back of their house from which
a splendid garden could be seen, which was full of the most beautiful
flowers and herbs. It was, however, surrounded by a high wall, and no
one dared to go into it because it belonged to an <character name="The Enchantress (Dame Gothel)" role="antagonist">enchantress</character>, who had
great power and was dreaded by all the world. One day the <character name="The Woman" role="wife">woman</character> was
standing by this window and looking down into the garden, when she saw a
bed which was planted with the most beautiful <define>rampion</define> (<character name="Rapunzel" role="protagonist">rapunzel</character>), and it
looked so fresh and green that she longed for it, she quite pined away,
and began to look pale and miserable. Then her husband was alarmed, and
asked: <dialog>‘What ails you, dear wife?’ ‘Ah,’</dialog> she replied, <dialog>‘if I can’t eat
some of the rampion, which is in the garden behind our house, I shall
die.’</dialog> The <character name="The Man" role="husband">man</character>, who loved her, thought: ‘Sooner than let your wife die,
bring her some of the rampion yourself, let it cost what it will.’
At twilight, he clambered down over the wall into the garden of the
<character name="The Enchantress (Dame Gothel)" role="antagonist">enchantress</character>, hastily clutched a handful of rampion, and took it to his
wife. She at once made herself a salad of it, and ate it greedily. It
tasted so good to her--so very good, that the next day she longed for it
three times as much as before. If he was to have any rest, her husband
must once more descend into the garden. In the gloom of evening
therefore, he let himself down again; but when he had clambered down the
wall he was terribly afraid, for he saw the <character name="The Enchantress (Dame Gothel)" role="antagonist">enchantress</character> standing before
him. <dialog>‘How can you dare,’</dialog> said she with angry look, <dialog>‘descend into my
garden and steal my rampion like a thief? You shall suffer for it!’
‘Ah,’</dialog> answered he, <dialog>‘let mercy take the place of justice, I only made
up my mind to do it out of necessity. My wife saw your rampion from the
window, and felt such a longing for it that she would have died if she
had not got some to eat.’</dialog> Then the <character name="The Enchantress (Dame Gothel)" role="antagonist">enchantress</character> allowed her anger to be
softened, and said to him: <dialog>‘If the case be as you say, I will allow
you to take away with you as much rampion as you will, only I make one
condition, you must give me the child which your wife will bring into
the world; it shall be well treated, and I will care for it like a
mother.’</dialog> The <character name="The Man" role="husband">man</character> in his terror consented to everything, and when the
<character name="The Woman" role="wife">woman</character> was brought to bed, the <character name="The Enchantress (Dame Gothel)" role="antagonist">enchantress</character> appeared at once, gave the
child the name of <character name="Rapunzel" role="protagonist">Rapunzel</character>, and took it away with her.</p>

<p><character name="Rapunzel" role="protagonist">Rapunzel</character> grew into the most beautiful child under the sun. When she was
twelve years old, the <character name="The Enchantress (Dame Gothel)" role="antagonist">enchantress</character> shut her into a tower, which lay in
a forest, and had neither stairs nor door, but quite at the top was a
little window. When the <character name="The Enchantress (Dame Gothel)" role="antagonist">enchantress</character> wanted to go in, she placed herself
beneath it and cried:

 <dialog>‘Rapunzel, Rapunzel,
  Let down your hair to me.’</dialog></p>

<p><character name="Rapunzel" role="protagonist">Rapunzel</character> had magnificent long hair, fine as spun gold, and when she
heard the voice of the <character name="The Enchantress (Dame Gothel)" role="antagonist">enchantress</character> she unfastened her braided <define>tresses</define>,
wound them round one of the hooks of the window above, and then the hair
fell twenty <define>ells</define> down, and the <character name="The Enchantress (Dame Gothel)" role="antagonist">enchantress</character> climbed up by it.</p>

<p>After a year or two, it came to pass that <character name="The King's Son" role="Prince">the king’s son</character> rode through
the forest and passed by the tower. Then he heard a song, which was so
charming that he stood still and listened. This was <character name="Rapunzel" role="protagonist">Rapunzel</character>, who in her
solitude passed her time in letting her sweet voice resound. <character name="The King's Son" role="Prince">The king’s
son</character> wanted to climb up to her, and looked for the door of the tower,
but none was to be found. He rode home, but the singing had so deeply
touched his heart, that every day he went out into the forest and
listened to it. Once when he was thus standing behind a tree, he saw
that an <character name="The Enchantress (Dame Gothel)" role="antagonist">enchantress</character> came there, and he heard how she cried:

 <dialog>‘Rapunzel, Rapunzel,
  Let down your hair to me.’</dialog></p>

<p>Then <character name="Rapunzel" role="protagonist">Rapunzel</character> let down the braids of her hair, and the <character name="The Enchantress (Dame Gothel)" role="antagonist">enchantress</character>
climbed up to her. ‘If that is the ladder by which one mounts, I too
will try my fortune,’ said he, and the next day when it began to grow
dark, he went to the tower and cried:

 <dialog>‘Rapunzel, Rapunzel,
  Let down your hair to me.’</dialog></p>

<p>Immediately the hair fell down and <character name="The King's Son" role="Prince">the king’s son</character> climbed up.</p>

<p>At first <character name="Rapunzel" role="protagonist">Rapunzel</character> was terribly frightened when a man, such as her eyes
had never yet beheld, came to her; but <character name="The King's Son" role="Prince">the king’s son</character> began to talk to
her quite like a friend, and told her that his heart had been so stirred
that it had let him have no rest, and he had been forced to see her.
Then <character name="Rapunzel" role="protagonist">Rapunzel</character> lost her fear, and when he asked her if she would take
him for her husband, and she saw that he was young and handsome, she
thought: ‘He will love me more than old Dame Gothel does’; and she said
yes, and laid her hand in his. She said: <dialog>‘I will willingly go away with
you, but I do not know how to get down. Bring with you a <define>skein of silk</define>
every time that you come, and I will weave a ladder with it, and when
that is ready I will descend, and you will take me on your horse.’</dialog> They
agreed that until that time he should come to her every evening, for the
old woman came by day. The <character name="The Enchantress (Dame Gothel)" role="antagonist">enchantress</character> remarked nothing of this, until
once <character name="Rapunzel" role="protagonist">Rapunzel</character> said to her: <dialog>‘Tell me, Dame Gothel, how it happens that
you are so much heavier for me to draw up than the young king’s son--he
is with me in a moment.’ ‘Ah! you wicked child,’</dialog> cried the <character name="The Enchantress (Dame Gothel)" role="antagonist">enchantress</character>.
<dialog>‘What do I hear you say! I thought I had separated you from all
the world, and yet you have deceived me!’</dialog> In her anger she clutched
<character name="Rapunzel" role="protagonist">Rapunzel</character>’s beautiful tresses, wrapped them twice round her left hand,
seized a pair of scissors with the right, and snip, snap, they were cut
off, and the lovely braids lay on the ground. And she was so pitiless
that she took poor <character name="Rapunzel" role="protagonist">Rapunzel</character> into a desert where she had to live in great
grief and misery.</p>

<p>On the same day that she cast out <character name="Rapunzel" role="protagonist">Rapunzel</character>, however, the <character name="The Enchantress (Dame Gothel)" role="antagonist">enchantress</character>
fastened the braids of hair, which she had cut off, to the hook of the
window, and when <character name="The King's Son" role="Prince">the king’s son</character> came and cried:

 <dialog>‘Rapunzel, Rapunzel,
  Let down your hair to me.’</dialog></p>

<p>she let the hair down. <character name="The King's Son" role="Prince">The king’s son</character> ascended, but instead of finding
his dearest <character name="Rapunzel" role="protagonist">Rapunzel</character>, he found the <character name="The Enchantress (Dame Gothel)" role="antagonist">enchantress</character>, who gazed at him with
wicked and venomous looks. <dialog>‘Aha!’</dialog> she cried mockingly, <dialog>‘you would fetch
your dearest, but the beautiful bird sits no longer singing in the nest;
the cat has got it, and will scratch out your eyes as well. <character name="Rapunzel" role="protagonist">Rapunzel</character> is
lost to you; you will never see her again.’</dialog> <character name="The King's Son" role="Prince">The king’s son</character> was beside
himself with pain, and in his despair he leapt down from the tower. He
escaped with his life, but the thorns into which he fell pierced his
eyes. Then he wandered quite blind about the forest, ate nothing but
roots and berries, and did naught but lament and weep over the loss of
his dearest wife. Thus he roamed about in misery for some years, and at
length came to the desert where <character name="Rapunzel" role="protagonist">Rapunzel</character>, with the twins to which she
had given birth, a boy and a girl, lived in wretchedness. He heard a
voice, and it seemed so familiar to him that he went towards it, and
when he approached, <character name="Rapunzel" role="protagonist">Rapunzel</character> knew him and fell on his neck and wept. Two
of her tears wetted his eyes and they grew clear again, and he could
see with them as before. He led her to his kingdom where he was
joyfully received, and they lived for a long time afterwards, happy and
contented.</p>
</story>
<theme>Freedom vs. Confinement</theme>


<story>
<title>SNOWDROP</title>

<p>It was the middle of winter, when the broad flakes of snow were falling
around, that the <character name="The Queen" role="Mother">queen</character> of a country many thousand miles off sat working
at her window. The frame of the window was made of fine black ebony, and
as she sat looking out upon the snow, she pricked her finger, and three
drops of blood fell upon it. Then she gazed thoughtfully upon the red
drops that sprinkled the white snow, and said, ‘Would that my little
daughter may be as white as that snow, as red as that blood, and as
black as this ebony windowframe!’ And so the little girl really did grow
up; her skin was as white as snow, her cheeks as rosy as the blood, and
her hair as black as ebony; and she was called <character name="Snowdrop" role="protagonist">Snowdrop</character>.</p>

<p>But this <character name="The Queen" role="Mother">queen</character> died; and the <character name="The King" role="Father">king</character> soon married another wife, who became
<character name="The New Queen" role="antagonist">queen</character>, and was very beautiful, but so vain that she could not bear
to think that anyone could be handsomer than she was. She had a fairy
<character name="Looking-glass" role="magic object">looking-glass</character>, to which she used to go, and then she would gaze upon
herself in it, and say:

 <dialog>‘Tell me, glass, tell me true!
  Of all the ladies in the land,
  Who is fairest, tell me, who?’</dialog></p>

<p>And the <character name="Looking-glass" role="magic object">glass</character> had always answered:

 <dialog>‘<slang>Thou</slang>, queen, <slang>art</slang> the fairest in all the land.’</dialog></p>

<p>But <character name="Snowdrop" role="protagonist">Snowdrop</character> grew more and more beautiful; and when she was seven years
old she was as bright as the day, and fairer than the <character name="The New Queen" role="antagonist">queen</character> herself.
Then the <character name="Looking-glass" role="magic object">glass</character> one day answered the <character name="The New Queen" role="antagonist">queen</character>, when she went to look in it
as usual:

<dialog>‘<slang>Thou</slang>, queen, <slang>art</slang> fair, and beauteous to see,
  But Snowdrop is lovelier far than thee!’</dialog></p>

<p>When she heard this she turned pale with rage and envy, and called to
one of her servants, and said, <dialog>‘Take Snowdrop away into the wide wood,
that I may never see her any more.’</dialog> Then the <character name="The Servant" role="Helper">servant</character> led her away; but
his heart melted when <character name="Snowdrop" role="protagonist">Snowdrop</character> begged him to spare her life, and he
said, <dialog>‘I will not hurt you, <slang>thou</slang> pretty child.’</dialog> So he left her by
herself; and though he thought it most likely that the wild beasts would
tear her in pieces, he felt as if a great weight were taken off his
heart when he had made up his mind not to kill her but to leave her to
her fate, with the chance of someone finding and saving her.</p>

<p>Then poor <character name="Snowdrop" role="protagonist">Snowdrop</character> wandered along through the wood in great fear; and
the wild beasts roared about her, but none did her any harm. In the
evening she came to a cottage among the hills, and went in to rest, for
her little feet would carry her no further. Everything was spruce and
neat in the cottage: on the table was spread a white cloth, and there
were seven little plates, seven little loaves, and seven little glasses
with wine in them; and seven knives and forks laid in order; and by
the wall stood seven little beds. As she was very hungry, she picked
a little piece of each loaf and drank a very little wine out of each
glass; and after that she thought she would lie down and rest. So she
tried all the little beds; but one was too long, and another was too
short, till at last the seventh suited her: and there she laid herself
down and went to sleep.</p>

<p>By and by in came the masters of the cottage. Now they were seven little
<character name="The Seven Dwarfs" role="Helpers">dwarfs</character>, that lived among the mountains, and dug and searched for gold.
They lighted up their seven lamps, and saw at once that all was not
right. The first said, <dialog>‘Who has been sitting on my stool?’</dialog> The second,
<dialog>‘Who has been eating off my plate?’</dialog> The third, <dialog>‘Who has been picking my
bread?’</dialog> The fourth, <dialog>‘Who has been meddling with my spoon?’</dialog> The fifth,
<dialog>‘Who has been handling my fork?’</dialog> The sixth, <dialog>‘Who has been cutting with
my knife?’</dialog> The seventh, <dialog>‘Who has been drinking my wine?’</dialog> Then the first
looked round and said, <dialog>‘Who has been lying on my bed?’</dialog> And the rest came
running to him, and everyone cried out that somebody had been upon his
bed. But the seventh saw <character name="Snowdrop" role="protagonist">Snowdrop</character>, and called all his brethren to come
and see her; and they cried out with wonder and astonishment and brought
their lamps to look at her, and said, <dialog>‘Good heavens! what a lovely child
she is!’</dialog> And they were very glad to see her, and took care not to wake
her; and the seventh dwarf slept an hour with each of the other <character name="The Seven Dwarfs" role="Helpers">dwarfs</character>
in turn, till the night was gone.</p>

<p>In the morning <character name="Snowdrop" role="protagonist">Snowdrop</character> told them all her story; and they pitied her,
and said if she would keep all things in order, and cook and wash and
knit and spin for them, she might stay where she was, and they would
take good care of her. Then they went out all day long to their work,
seeking for gold and silver in the mountains: but <character name="Snowdrop" role="protagonist">Snowdrop</character> was left at
home; and they warned her, and said, <dialog>‘The queen will soon find out where
you are, so take care and let no one in.’</dialog></p>

<p>But the <character name="The New Queen" role="antagonist">queen</character>, now that she thought <character name="Snowdrop" role="protagonist">Snowdrop</character> was dead, believed that she
must be the handsomest lady in the land; and she went to her <character name="Looking-glass" role="magic object">glass</character> and
said:

 <dialog>‘Tell me, glass, tell me true!
  Of all the ladies in the land,
  Who is fairest, tell me, who?’</dialog></p>

<p>And the <character name="Looking-glass" role="magic object">glass</character> answered:

 <dialog>‘<slang>Thou</slang>, queen, <slang>art</slang> the fairest in all this land:
  But over the hills, in the greenwood shade,
  Where the seven dwarfs their dwelling have made,
  There Snowdrop is hiding her head; and she
  Is lovelier far, O queen! than thee.’</dialog></p>

<p>Then the <character name="The New Queen" role="antagonist">queen</character> was very much frightened; for she knew that the <character name="Looking-glass" role="magic object">glass</character>
always spoke the truth, and was sure that the <character name="The Servant" role="Helper">servant</character> had betrayed her.
And she could not bear to think that anyone lived who was more beautiful
than she was; so she dressed herself up as an old pedlar, and went
her way over the hills, to the place where the <character name="The Seven Dwarfs" role="Helpers">dwarfs</character> dwelt. Then she
knocked at the door, and cried, <dialog>‘Fine <slang>wares</slang> to sell!’</dialog> <character name="Snowdrop" role="protagonist">Snowdrop</character> looked
out at the window, and said, <dialog>‘Good day, good woman! what have you to
sell?’ ‘Good <slang>wares</slang>, fine <slang>wares</slang>,’</dialog> said she; <dialog>‘laces and bobbins of all
colours.’</dialog> ‘I will let the old lady in; she seems to be a very good
sort of body,’ thought <character name="Snowdrop" role="protagonist">Snowdrop</character>, as she ran down and unbolted the door.
<dialog>‘Bless me!’</dialog> said the old woman, <dialog>‘how badly your stays are laced! Let me
lace them up with one of my nice new laces.’</dialog> <character name="Snowdrop" role="protagonist">Snowdrop</character> did not dream of
any mischief; so she stood before the old woman; but she set to work
so nimbly, and pulled the lace so tight, that <character name="Snowdrop" role="protagonist">Snowdrop</character>’s breath was
stopped, and she fell down as if she were dead. <dialog>‘There’s an end to all
thy beauty,’</dialog> said the spiteful <character name="The New Queen" role="antagonist">queen</character>, and went away home.</p>

<p>In the evening the seven <character name="The Seven Dwarfs" role="Helpers">dwarfs</character> came home; and I need not say how
grieved they were to see their faithful <character name="Snowdrop" role="protagonist">Snowdrop</character> stretched out upon the
ground, as if she was quite dead. However, they lifted her up, and when
they found what ailed her, they cut the lace; and in a little time she
began to breathe, and very soon came to life again. Then they said, <dialog>‘The
old woman was the queen herself; take care another time, and let no one
in when we are away.’</dialog></p>

<p>When the <character name="The New Queen" role="antagonist">queen</character> got home, she went straight to her <character name="Looking-glass" role="magic object">glass</character>, and spoke to it
as before; but to her great grief it still said:

 <dialog>‘<slang>Thou</slang>, queen, <slang>art</slang> the fairest in all this land:
  But over the hills, in the greenwood shade,
  Where the seven dwarfs their dwelling have made,
  There Snowdrop is hiding her head; and she
  Is lovelier far, O queen! than thee.’</dialog></p>

<p>Then the blood ran cold in her heart with spite and malice, to see that
<character name="Snowdrop" role="protagonist">Snowdrop</character> still lived; and she dressed herself up again, but in quite
another dress from the one she wore before, and took with her a poisoned
comb. When she reached the <character name="The Seven Dwarfs" role="Helpers">dwarfs</character>’ cottage, she knocked at the door, and
cried, <dialog>‘Fine <slang>wares</slang> to sell!’</dialog> But <character name="Snowdrop" role="protagonist">Snowdrop</character> said, <dialog>‘I dare not let anyone
in.’</dialog> Then the <character name="The New Queen" role="antagonist">queen</character> said, <dialog>‘Only look at my beautiful combs!’</dialog> and gave
her the poisoned one. And it looked so pretty, that she took it up and
put it into her hair to try it; but the moment it touched her head,
the poison was so powerful that she fell down senseless. <dialog>‘There you may
lie,’</dialog> said the <character name="The New Queen" role="antagonist">queen</character>, and went her way. But by good luck the <character name="The Seven Dwarfs" role="Helpers">dwarfs</character>
came in very early that evening; and when they saw <character name="Snowdrop" role="protagonist">Snowdrop</character> lying on
the ground, they thought what had happened, and soon found the poisoned
comb. And when they took it away she got well, and told them all that
had passed; and they warned her once more not to open the door to
anyone.</p>

<p>Meantime the <character name="The New Queen" role="antagonist">queen</character> went home to her <character name="Looking-glass" role="magic object">glass</character>, and shook with rage when she
read the very same answer as before; and she said, <dialog>‘Snowdrop shall die,
if it cost me my life.’</dialog> So she went by herself into her chamber, and got
ready a poisoned apple: the outside looked very rosy and tempting, but
whoever tasted it was sure to die. Then she dressed herself up as a
peasant’s wife, and travelled over the hills to the <character name="The Seven Dwarfs" role="Helpers">dwarfs</character>’ cottage,
and knocked at the door; but <character name="Snowdrop" role="protagonist">Snowdrop</character> put her head out of the window and
said, <dialog>‘I dare not let anyone in, for the <character name="The Seven Dwarfs" role="Helpers">dwarfs</character> have told me not.’ ‘Do
as you please,’</dialog> said the old woman, <dialog>‘but at any rate take this pretty
apple; I will give it you.’ ‘No,’</dialog> said <character name="Snowdrop" role="protagonist">Snowdrop</character>, <dialog>‘I dare not take it.’
‘You silly girl!’</dialog> answered the other, <dialog>‘what are you afraid of? Do you
think it is poisoned? Come! do you eat one part, and I will eat the
other.’</dialog> Now the apple was so made up that one side was good, though the
other side was poisoned. Then <character name="Snowdrop" role="protagonist">Snowdrop</character> was much tempted to taste, for
the apple looked so very nice; and when she saw the old woman eat, she
could wait no longer. But she had scarcely put the piece into her mouth,
when she fell down dead upon the ground. <dialog>‘This time nothing will save
thee,’</dialog> said the <character name="The New Queen" role="antagonist">queen</character>; and she went home to her <character name="Looking-glass" role="magic object">glass</character>, and at last it
said:

 <dialog>‘<slang>Thou</slang>, queen, <slang>art</slang> the fairest of all the fair.’</dialog></p>

<p>And then her wicked heart was glad, and as happy as such a heart could
be.</p>

<p>When evening came, and the <character name="The Seven Dwarfs" role="Helpers">dwarfs</character> had gone home, they found <character name="Snowdrop" role="protagonist">Snowdrop</character>
lying on the ground: no breath came from her lips, and they were afraid
that she was quite dead. They lifted her up, and combed her hair, and
washed her face with wine and water; but all was in vain, for the little
girl seemed quite dead. So they laid her down upon a <define>bier</define>, and all seven
watched and bewailed her three whole days; and then they thought they
would bury her: but her cheeks were still rosy; and her face looked just
as it did while she was alive; so they said, <dialog>‘We will never bury her in
the cold ground.’</dialog> And they made a coffin of glass, so that they might
still look at her, and wrote upon it in golden letters what her name
was, and that she was a king’s daughter. And the coffin was set among
the hills, and one of the <character name="The Seven Dwarfs" role="Helpers">dwarfs</character> always sat by it and watched. And the
birds of the air came too, and <define>bemoaned</define> <character name="Snowdrop" role="protagonist">Snowdrop</character>; and first of all came
an owl, and then a raven, and at last a dove, and sat by her side.</p>

<p>And thus <character name="Snowdrop" role="protagonist">Snowdrop</character> lay for a long, long time, and still only looked as
though she was asleep; for she was even now as white as snow, and as red
as blood, and as black as ebony. At last a <character name="The Prince" role="hero">dwarfs</character> came and called at the
<character name="The Seven Dwarfs" role="Helpers">dwarfs</character>’ house; and he saw <character name="Snowdrop" role="protagonist">Snowdrop</character>, and read what was written in golden
letters. Then he offered the <character name="The Seven Dwarfs" role="Helpers">dwarfs</character> money, and prayed and besought them
to let him take her away; but they said, <dialog>‘We will not part with her for
all the gold in the world.’</dialog> At last, however, they had pity on him, and
gave him the coffin; but the moment he lifted it up to carry it home
with him, the piece of apple fell from between her lips, and <character name="Snowdrop" role="protagonist">Snowdrop</character>
awoke, and said, <dialog>‘Where am I?’</dialog> And the <character name="The Prince" role="hero">dwarfs</character> said, <dialog>‘<slang>Thou art</slang> quite safe
with me.’</dialog></p>

<p>Then he told her all that had happened, and said, <dialog>‘I love you far better
than all the world; so come with me to my father’s palace, and you shall
be my wife.’</dialog> And <character name="Snowdrop" role="protagonist">Snowdrop</character> consented, and went home with the <character name="The Prince" role="hero">dwarfs</character>;
and everything was got ready with great pomp and splendour for their
wedding.</p>

<p>To the feast was asked, among the rest, <character name="Snowdrop" role="protagonist">Snowdrop</character>’s old enemy the <character name="The New Queen" role="antagonist">queen</character>;
and as she was dressing herself in fine rich clothes, she looked in the
<character name="Looking-glass" role="magic object">glass</character> and said:

 <dialog>‘Tell me, glass, tell me true!
  Of all the ladies in the land,
  Who is fairest, tell me, who?’</dialog></p>

<p>And the <character name="Looking-glass" role="magic object">glass</character> answered:

 <dialog>‘<slang>Thou</slang>, lady, <slang>art</slang> loveliest here, I <slang>ween</slang>;
  But lovelier far is the new-made queen.’</dialog></p>

<p>When she heard this she started with rage; but her envy and curiosity
were so great, that she could not help setting out to see the bride. And
when she got there, and saw that it was no other than <character name="Snowdrop" role="protagonist">Snowdrop</character>, who, as
she thought, had been dead a long while, she choked with rage, and fell
down and died: but <character name="Snowdrop" role="protagonist">Snowdrop</character> and the <character name="The Prince" role="hero">dwarfs</character> lived and reigned happily
over that land many, many years; and sometimes they went up into the
mountains, and paid a visit to the little <character name="The Seven Dwarfs" role="Helpers">dwarfs</character>, who had been so kind
to <character name="Snowdrop" role="protagonist">Snowdrop</character> in her time of need.</p>
</story>
<theme>Jealousy and Envy</theme>

</text>
</xml>
